Laves mss., 1924-1980 LMC 3006
Lilly Library
Laves mss.
1924-1980
Lilly Library
Laves, Walter H. C. (Walter Herman Carl), 1902-1983
LMC 3006
28 Boxes
2 folios oversize
Consists of the papers of Indiana University professor Walter Herman Carl Laves, 1902-1983.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Walter Herman Carl Laves, 1902-1983, was an Indiana University professor. A native of Chicago, he received his degrees from the University of Chicago and held positions first at Hamilton College and then at the University of Chicago before coming to Indiana University. He served as chairman of the Department of Political Science from 1954 to 1966, was honored as the first holder of the Wendell L. Willkie Professorship in Political Science, and retired from the University in 1972.
In the interval between his positions at Chicago and Indiana, during World War II and later, Laves had a career in public service. He served successively in the Office of Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, the Office of Civilian Defense, and from 1943 to 1947, in the Bureau of the Budget as consultant in international affairs. He was present at the founding conferences of the United Nations and United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization and served in advisory capacity to the American delegation at the initial session of the United Nations in London. From 1947 to 1950 Laves was the Deputy Director General of UNESCO in Paris. Subsequently, he was twice a member of the United States delegation to the UNESCO general conference and chairman of the U.S. National Commission for UNESCO.
He was the co-author with Charles Alexander Thomson of UNESCO: Purpose, Progress and Prospects which in 1958 won an Indiana Author's Day citation. He also authored Cultural Relations and U.S. Foreign Policy, published in 1963, in addition to many articles for journals.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: I. Biographical; II. Correspondence; III. Diaries; IV. Financial; V. Indiana University; VI. Photographs; VII. Subjects; VIII. Writings; IX. Printed; X. Memorabilia.
Scope and Content Note
The Laves mss., 1924-1980, consists of the papers of Indiana University professor Walter Herman Carl Laves, 1902-1983. The collection includes biographical material, correspondence, diaries, financial materials, materials related to Indiana University, photographs, subject files, writings, printed materials, and memorabilia.
The Subjects series contain materials related to his many activities and interests, such as community development, the Office of Civil Defense, his many trips abroad, and various meetings and conferences.
Printed materials include tear sheets and reprints of his publications in various journals, clippings related to Laves' activities. Also present are publications by his father, Kurt Laves, 1866-1944, professor of astronomy at the University of Chicago.
Memorabilia consists mostly of award certificates and citations. There are also insignia and medals awarded to Laves from the government of Thailand. Completing this section is a Thai temple rubbing depicting a scene from the Ramakien legend.
Acquisition Information
Gift. 1982
Political scientists--Indiana--Bloomington--Correspondence.; Political science--Study and teaching--United States; Indiana University; International relations; Indiana University. Department of Political Science; Indiana University
- Biographical, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes address book and passports.
- Correspondence
  Additional correspondence may be found throughout the collection. Consult the Manuscripts Index in the Library for dates of letters of individual correspondents.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1924, May 28 - 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948 - 1952, Aug. (Box 2)
  - 1952, Sept. - 1955 (Box 3)
  - 1956 - 1969, June (Box 4)
  - 1969, July - 1977 (Box 5)
- Diaries
  Both loose leaf and bound. Includes aide memoirs and memoranda.
  - 1936 - 1942 (Box 5)
  - 1942 (cont.) - 1947 (Box 6)
  - 1947 (cont.) - 1953 (Box 7)
  - 1954 - 1976 (Box 8)
- Financial
  - Grant: United Nations Assistance in Political Development (Box 8)
    - Finances, 1963-1967 (Box 8)
    - Proposal drafts, 1963-1965; (4 folders) (Box 8)
    - Report to Carnegie, July 1, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Receipts, 1947-1950; 1956-1957; (3 folders) (Box 8)
    Mostly from hotels and restaurants
- Indiana University (Box 9)
  - Government Department (Box 9)
    - Correspondence (inter-departmental), 1964-1966 (Box 9)
    - Class materials for G 417, 1969 (Box 9)
    - Class materials for G 623 (International Organization), 1965/66; (4 folders) (Box 9)
    - Class notes for G 669, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Development, 1956-1966; (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Executive Committee Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 9)
    - Faculty, 1961-1966 (Box 9)
    - Notes, 1963-1966 (Box 9)
  - International Relations Research Center., 1962 (Box 9)
  - John Watson Foster Project, undated (Box 9)
  - Latin American Studies (Box 9)
  - Mini-University lectureNotes, June 25, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Non-Western Areas in Indiana Undergraduate Education: Bloomington Conference, Sept. 18-20, 1958 (Box 9)
  - Social Studies Development Center, 1968 (Box 9)
  - Sub-Committee on Governmental Contracts, May 16, 1960 (Box 9)
- Photographs
  - Huxley, Julian Sorell, 1948 (Box 9)
  - Laves, Ruth (Wilson), undated (Box 9)
  - Laves, Walter Herman Carl, 1943-1973 (Box 9)
    Includes group photographs.
  - Thailand, 1955 (Box 9)
  - Thailand, 1964; (2 folders) (Box 9)
    Includes album, additional loose photographs and clippings.
  - UN Exhibit, 1943 (Box 9)
- Subjects (Box 9)
  Subject headings were assigned by Laves and are arranged alphabetically.
  - African Trip, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Itinerary and Personal expenses, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Summary and Activities, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Conclusions (Box 9)
    - Afghanistan (Box 9)
    - Egypt, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Ethiopia, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Ethiopia (cont.) (Box 10)
    - Ghana (Box 10)
    - Iran, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Israel (Box 10)
    - Ivory Coast (Box 10)
    - Kenya, (3 folders) (Box 10)
    - Lebanon (Box 10)
    - Libya (Box 10)
    - Nigeria, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Senegal (Box 10)
    - Sudan, (2 folders) (Box 10)
    - Tanzania (Box 10)
    - Tunisia (Box 10)
    - Uganda (Box 10)
  - American Council on Education Conference, 1965 (Box 10)
  - American Society for Public Administration, 1963-1967 (Box 10)
  - Asian Trip, 1959 (Box 10)
  - Community Development (Box 10)
    - Analysis of potential contribution of community development to political development. Draft, undated (Box 10)
    - Community Development Research model, 1969 (Box 10)
    - Cooperative, 1966-1967 (Box 10)
    - The Development of the Colonial Small Community, 1953 (Box 10)
    - Forward Look in Community Development, 1965-1966 (Box 10)
    - Horn, Donna. Two papers on Community Development, 1965-1966 (Box 10)
    - International Development Center, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
    - Materials, 1956-1966 (Box 10)
    - Valsan, E.H. Two papers on Community Development, 1963 (Box 10)
    - Training for Basic Democracy in Pakistan, 1960 (Box 10)
  - Dag Hammarskjold Conference, Denver, (2 folders) (Box 10)
  - Dag Hammarskjold Conference, Denver (cont.), (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Division of Inter-American Activities in the United States, 1942; (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - Exchange of professional, scholarly and scientific persons. Princeton Conference, Dec. 2-4, 1954 (Box 11)
  - Food and Agriculture Organization. Interviewsnotes, 1963-1964; 1966-1967; (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Government Organization for Foreign Relations (State Department), 1944-1946; (4 folders) (Box 11)
  - Human Rights, 1967-1968; (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - India, 1957; 1966; (2 folders) (Box 11)
  - International Development, 1975-1980 (Box 11)
  - International Development Seminar, Honolulu, Aug. 9-Sept. 3, 1965; (9 folders) (Box 11)
  - International Development Seminar, Honolulu, Aug. 9-Sept. 3, 1965; (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - International Education Program, 1965 (Box 12)
  - International Labor Organization (Box 12)
    - Geneva, 1967; (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Africa, 1966 (Box 12)
    - Interviews, 1963 (Box 12)
    - Inventory, 1966 (Box 12)
    - Working Party Reports, 1964-1966 (Box 12)
  - International Political Science Association, Brussels Conference, Sept. 18-23, 1967; (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - International Studies Association, 1971-1975; (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Interregional Expert Meeting on Social Welfare Organization and Administration, Geneva, Aug. 7-18, 1967; (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Interviews in relation to project, 1963-1965 (Box 12)
  - Kabul University, 1972-1973; (2 folders) (Box 12)
  - Korean Trip, 1968; (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Lagos Conference, 1971; (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Land Reform, 1965-1968 (Box 12)
  - Land Reform by Shaedal, 1965-1969 (Box 12)
  - League of Nations Association. Mid-West Office, 1936-1939 (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - London, 1963 (Box 13)
  - Malaysia, 1964-1966 (Box 13)
  - Moscow/Kiev, 1973 (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Murphy Report (American Legion), 1955-1956 (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Mutual and Cultural Exchange Act of 1961 (Fulbright Act), 1960-1961 (Box 13)
  - National Association for Foreign Students Affairs, 1973 (Box 13)
  - Office of Civilian Defense (Box 13)
    - General, 1942-1943; (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Office of War Information, 1943; (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Victory Speakers Directors Meeting, Mar. 12-13, 1943 (Box 13)
  - Office of Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, 1941-1942; (4 folders) (Box 13)
  - Pakistan trip, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Pakistan, 1964-1966 (Box 14)
  - Paris, 1963 (Box 14)
  - Personnel potential, 1952 (Box 14)
  - Philippines trip, 1953 (Box 14)
  - Philippines, 1965-1966 (Box 14)
  - Political and Economic Development Literature, 1962 (Box 14)
  - Political Conditions in LDCs, 1975-1976 (Box 14)
  - Political Development, various papers by Fraser, Haviland and Morse, 1966 (Box 14)
  - Political Development Assistance by UN organizations, 1964-1972; (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Rangoon Conference, Mar. 15-30, 1954; (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Rome, 1967 (Box 14)
  - Sweden, 1949 (Box 14)
  - Thailand (Box 14)
    - Thammasat University, 1955-1959; 1963-1964; (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1966-1968 (Box 14)
  - United Nations Research Institute on Social Development, Geneva, 1964-1966 (Box 14)
  - United Nations Inventory and Direct Assistance, 1966 (Box 14)
  - UNESCO, 1946-1977; (7 folders) (Box 14)
  - UNESCO(cont.), 1946-1977; (7 folders) (Box 15)
  - UNESCO Experts, 1951-1970 (Box 15)
  - UNESCO Institute for Education, 1955 (Box 15)
  - U.S. Advisory Commission on Education Exchange. 45th Meeting46th Meeting, 48th Meeting, 1960; 1961; (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - U.S. Relations to International Organization, 1944-1945 (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan. Suggestions for Vandenberg Foreign Policy Center, 1951 (Box 15)
  - Washington, 1966 (Box 15)
  - World Bank, 1965 (Box 15)
  - World Health Organization, 1963-1964 (Box 15)
- Writings
  Arranged into the following subseries: Writings by Laves, Speeches by Laves, and Writings by Others.
  General
  Additional writings by Laves and others may be found in the series Printed.
  - Writings by Laves
    Research and drafts of chapters for a book on international administration and cooperation completes this section.
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - 14 Questions and Answers about UNESCO, 1954 (Box 15)
    - Civil and Political Rights in the Context of Development Assistance, a paper prepared for the International Conference on Human Rights, 1968 (Box 15)
    - Community Development and the development of capacity for self-government--the role of the United Nations, 1966 (Box 15)
    - Give Joe Doakes a Chance., 1945 (Box 15)
    - Impact of ECA [Economic Cooperative Administration], 1951; (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - International Administration., 1953; (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - The Organization and Conduct of United States Foreign Service., 1946 (Box 15)
    - Problems of Administration of the Foreign Service Act of 1946. (Box 15)
    - The Reorganization of the Department of State., 1946 (Box 15)
    - Report of the West Indies - South America Administrative Survey Group, submitted, May 26, 1945; (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - The United Nations: Reorganizing the World's Governmental Institutions, 1945 (Box 15)
    - United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural OrganizationFor The Encyclopedia of Education, 1971 (Box 15)
    - The United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization. Statement prepared at the request of Mrs. Dana C. Backus for use as a forward for an issue of 'United Nations News for Women Broadcasters' a monthly radio clip-sheet, 1953 (Box 15)
    - UNESCO: Center of Cultural DiplomacyChapter XX of Diplomacy in a Changing World, edited by Stephen D. Kertesz and M.A. Fitzsimmons (Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame Press, 1959). Page proofs (Box 15)
    - UNESCO: Purpose, Progress, Prospects (with Charles A. Thomson)Page proofs, 1957 (Box 15)
    - The United States German Claims Settlement, 1925/26 (Box 15)
    - Were in the UNO now, 1945 (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous writings by Laves (Box 15)
      - Reviews of books by other writers, 1958-1965 (Box 15)
      - Notes on WHO, 1948 (Box 15)
      - Writing projects. notes, Undated (Box 15)
      - Untitled. re: ...some major problems of governmental organization to be faced by the United States after the war..., 1946 (Box 15)
    - International administration and cooperation book (Box 15)
      - Research (Box 16)
      - Research (cont.) (Box 17)
      - Research (cont.) (Box 18)
      - Research (cont.), (5 folders) (Box 19)
      - Research (cont.) (Box 20)
      - Drafts of chapters, (36 folders) (Box 20)
      - Drafts of chapters (cont.) (Box 21)
      - Drafts of chapters (cont.), (23 folders) (Box 22)
  - Speeches
    Includes press releases, radio interviews, and hearings in Congress.
    A detailed list of the speeches is available in the Lilly Library.
    - 1936-1966, (16 folders) (Box 22)
    - 1967-1968, (2 folders) (Box 23)
  - Writings by Others
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - LePawsky, Albert Agenda for International Training.(proof), 1962 (Box 23)
    - Lindesmith, Gertrude W. The Individual Needs and Adjustments of The Participant Graduate Student., 1967; (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Schaffner, Joseph Halle, et al. Report (summary) of the Africa-Middle East Survey Group on the Administrative Level of the Foreign Service. Copy D., 1945 (Box 23)
    - Silvert, Karl and Frank Bonilla. Education and the social meaning of Development., 1961 (Box 23)
    - Van Vorys, Karl. [Pakistan], 1961 (Box 23)
    - Warfield, Ethelbert, et al. Report of the European Administrative Survey Group. Copy D., 1945 (Box 23)
- Printed
  Arranged by materials written by or relating to Laves (writings, Congressional hearing testimonies, and programs and announcements for his speeches and lectures), miscellaneous reprints and articles by other writers, including writings by Laves' father Kurt Laves, and clippings.
  - Laves, Walter Herman Carl (Box 23)
    - Writings, 1926-1952; (14 folders) (Box 23)
      Contains mostly journals and reprints from journals.
    - Writings, 1953-1975; (14 folders) (Box 24)
    - Congressional hearing testimonies, 1942-1957; (4 folders) (Box 24)
    - Congressional hearing testimonies, 1958-1961; (2 folders) (Box 25)
    - Programs and announcements for speeches and lectures by WHCL, (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Writings by Others (Box 25)
    - Laves, Kurt. Various papers, mostly relating to astronomy and memorial service programs, (3 folders) (Box 25)
    - Pocket-sized copies: Covenant of the League of Nationsand Charter of the United Nations and Statute of the International Court of Justice, ca. 1930; undated (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous writers, 1937-1964; (11 folders) (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous writers, 1965-1976; (4 folders) (Box 26)
  - Clippings concerning Laves (Box 26)
    - 1936-1974, (7 folders) (Box 26)
    - Scrapbook, 1937-1938 (Box 26)
  - Clippings concerning miscellaneous topics, 1931-1971; (4 folders) (Box 26)
- Memorabilia
  - Realia (Box 26)
    - Thailand. Order of the Crown insignia. In blue velvet case (Box 26)
    - Thailand. Order of the White Elephant insignia. In red velvet case (Box 26)
    - Thailand. Two hand-made, replica Thai swords. ca. 7 inches in length. In light-blue and gold box. (Box 26)
    - Unidentified pin with crossed machetes (Box 26)
  - Awards, citations, etc.
    - Department of State. Appointment as U.S. representative and vice chairman of delegation, 7th Session of General Conference of UNESCO, Paris, 1952, Nov. 12 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University Writers Conference Award for work on World Affairs by Indiana author: UNESCO: Purpose, Progress, Prospects, by Laves and Charles A. Thomas, 1958, Apr. 20 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University sends felicitations...conveyed by Walter Laves to Thammasat University in Thailand, 1964, Oct. 8 (Ovflat 36)
    - Order of the Crown. Conferred by the King of Thailand. In English and Thai, 1964, Oct. 8 (Ovflat 36)
    - The President of the United States. Appointment as alternate representative to the 13th Session of UNESCO. Signed by Lyndon Johnson and Dean Rusk, 1964, Oct. 17 (Ovflat 36)
    - Order of the White Elephant. Conferred by the King of Thailand. In English and Thai. Accompanied by instructions for wearing the insignia, 1968, Mar. 11 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University, Century-And-A-Half Club, 1970, June 19 (Ovflat 36)
    - Department of State. Appointment as member of the U.S. Commission for UNESCO. Signed by William P. Rogers, 1971, July 6 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University. Recognition of 18 years of service upon retirement from teaching, 1972, May 2 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University. Membership in the Emeritus Club, 1972, May 13 (Ovflat 36)
    - University of Chicago, Emeritus Club. 50th anniversary of graduation, 1973, June. (Ovflat 36)
    - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO. In appreciation as vice-chairman, 1973, Nov. 17 (Ovflat 36)
    - International Society for Educational, Cultural, and Scientific Interchanges. First annual award, 1974, Mar. 20 (Ovflat 36)
    - International Studies Association. In appreciation for support in Take-The-Pledge Campaign, 1974, May 17 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University, Mini-University. In appreciation for having taught courses, 1975, June 20 (Ovflat 36)
    - Indiana University, Mini-University. In appreciation for having taught courses, 1975, June 25 (Ovflat 36)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica. Welcomes Laves as one of its contributors, Undated. (Ovflat 36)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - Dag Hammarskjold. Black and white stylized print by Olav S. Matheisen., ca 1961; (4 copies) (Box 26, Folder Folio)
  - Temple rubbing from Thailand. Black on rice paper (Ovflat 36, Folder Folio)